{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man once walked all the way across Virginia lengthwise to secure a promised spot in\ncollege at Hampton. He promised to keep \"as separate as the five fingers on each hand\" and\nadvocated that his followers \"cast down your bucket where you are.\" For 10 points, name this\nman whose Atlanta Compromise speech staked out a moderate civil rights position in 1895.",
      "answer": [
        "Booker T. Washington",
        "Washington"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Early objects created using this device are called incunabula. This device was introduced to\nVenice by Aldus Manutius and brought to England by William Caxton. A goldsmith from Mainz\nused a screw-press for his \"movable-type\" version of this device. For 10 points, name this device\nfirst created in the West by Johannes Gutenberg.",
      "answer": "printing press"
    },
    {
      "question": "Between political offices, this man was a law partner of future FCC commissioner Newton\nMinnow. This man snapped \"don't wait for the translation\" at Valerin Zorin during his time as\nU.S. ambassador to the United Nations. He was dubbed \"egghead\" during his two failed\nPresidential runs. For 10 points, name this man who lost twice to Dwight Eisenhower.",
      "answer": [
        "Adlai Stevenson",
        "Stevenson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was once marooned on Bermuda in the wreck of the Sea Venture. He created the\nOrinoco cultivar of a product that he put into four barels during his return to England, where he\npresented his wife, under the new name \"Rebecca,\" to the royal court. For 10 points, name this\nhusband of Pocahontas who devised the financially viable form of American tobacco.",
      "answer": [
        "John Rolfe",
        "Rolfe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1861, Johann Reis arguably accomplished this task by making use of magneto-restriction.\nElisha Gray claimed to have accomplished this task, though he lost out on a patent to the man\nwho is generally credited with this accomplishment and used the result to transmit, \"Watson,\ncome here, I want you.\" For 10 points, name this achievement of Alexander Graham Bell.",
      "answer": [
        "inventing the telephone",
        "telephone"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "President-in-waiting Luis Donaldo Colosio was assassinated in this city in 1994. This city's\nAvenida Revolución (ah-veh-NEE-duh reh-voh-loo-see-OWN) was the location of Cesar\nCardini's restaurant, where the Caesar salad was invented. For 10 points, name this city in Baja\nCalifornia which attracts numerous American tourists from nearby San Diego.",
      "answer": "Tijuana"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city constructed a paved road used to transport boats overland called the Diolkos. A\ndispute between this city and its colony of Corcyra was a cause of the Peloponnesian War.\nCypselid rulers of this city included its second tyrant, Periander. Capitals bedecked with\nacanthus leaves characterized this city’s namesake order of columns. For 10 points, name this\nancient Greek city located on a namesake isthmus.",
      "answer": [
        "Corinth",
        "Korinthos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem which became a protest song about this activity compares the \"scent of magnolias,\nsweet and fresh\" to the \"sudden smell of burning flesh.\" Federal attempts to crack down on this\npractice included the Dyer Bill. Ida B. Wells was an activist against this practice, which is the\nsubject of \"Strange Fruit.\" For 10 points, identify this practice of extrajudicial mob killings of\nblacks.",
      "answer": [
        "lynchings"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One holder of this title boasted that his descendants would rule for 10,000 generations, though\ncounting him they ruled for only two. That holder of this title followed Legalist precepts while\nburning subversive books and died after taking mercury pills in search of immortality. For 10\npoints, name this title taken by Qin Shi Huang and later used by leaders of the Han dynasty.",
      "answer": [
        "emperor of China",
        "huangdi",
        "di"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader forcibly dismissed the Rump Parliament and replaced it with Barebone’s\nparliament. He was hated in Ireland for atrocities committed at Wexford and Drogheda. He\nhelped win the Battle of Naseby as a cavalry commander in the New Model Army. For 10 points,\nname this man who served as Lord Protector of England in the interregnum following the\nexecution of Charles I of England.",
      "answer": [
        "Oliver Cromwell",
        "Cromwell"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The Trung Sisters are national heroes of what Southeast Asian country's resistance to\nChinese occupation?",
      "answer": "Vietnam"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This product was named by Rowland Hanson, who shot down the proposed name \"Interface\nManager.\" In 1992, this product's manufacturer decided to focus on it and stop developing OS/2.\nThis product's popular versions included 3.1, NT, and 95, prior to the release of version 7 in\n2009. For 10 points, name this operating system produced by Microsoft.",
        "answer": "Windows"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "OS/2 was a joint project of Microsoft and what former titan of the industry, known as\n\"Big Blue\" for the color of both its logo and its once-mandatory employee ties?",
        "answer": "IBM"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was advised by the author of Germany is Our Problem, Henry Morgenthau, as well\nas by a man who later became a conservative, Raymond Moley. This man's unofficial advisors\nwere recruited largely from Columbia University's law school and were led by Rexford Tugwell.\nThe \"brain trust\" advised, for 10 points, what man during his four terms as U.S. President?",
        "answer": [
          "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
          "F Roosevelt",
          "FDR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Roosevelt was more formally advised by what Secretary of War during World War II,\nwho had previously articulated a namesake \"doctrine\" refusing to recognize Japanese conquests\nas Secretary of State?",
        "answer": [
          "Henry Stimson",
          "Stimson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire followed the proclamation of the Edict of Gulhane with a fifty year modernization\neffort called the Tanzimat Reforms. Some of its armies were composed of irregular “bashibazouks,” while others were composed of janissaries. It was known as the Sick Man of Europe\nleading up to World War I. For 10 points, name this empire which centered on Turkey.",
        "answer": [
          "Ottoman Empire",
          "Ottoman"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first president of modern Turkey was what man who implemented a namesake\npolicy of strict westernization?",
        "answer": [
          "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
          "Ataturk"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A major genre innovation during this period was the concerto grosso (con-CHAIR-toe\nGROSS-oh), which was used extensively by Arcangelo Corelli. Another composer from this\nmusical period wrote the Goldberg Variations. For 10 points, name this period in Western music\nhistory that included Johann Sebastian Bach, and came between the Renaissance and Classical\neras.",
        "answer": "Baroque"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bach composed six concertos for Christian Ludwig, who held the symbolic title of\nMargrave of what state surrounding Potsdam, Germany?",
        "answer": "Brandenburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This song asks \"where is that band who so vaultingly swore\" and observes \"where the foes'\nhaughty host in dread silence reposes\" in its little-heard additional verses. The British bar song\nsong \"To Anacreon in Heaven\" was used to set the lyrics of this song. For 10 points, name this\nsong written during the British bombardment of Fort McHenry by Francis Scott Key.",
        "answer": "The Star-Spangled Banner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fort McHenry is found guarding the harbor of what major city?",
        "answer": "Baltimore"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A state park named for these people contains the Pioneer Monument and the Emigrant Trail\nMuseum. This group of people suffered an early tragedy when John Snyder was murdered. This\ngroup's poor decision to attempt the Hastings Cutoff led to them being snowed in at Truckee\nLake. For 10 points, name these people who resorted to cannibalism in the 1840s.",
        "answer": [
          "Donner Party",
          "Donner"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hastings Cutoff took the Donner Party south of what large body of water some\nmonths before they reached the Sierra Nevadas?",
        "answer": "Great Salt Lake"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Martial law was declared in this nation after the First Quarter Storm. Cardinal Jaime Sin\nhelped spearhead the overthrow of one leader of this nation. That leader’s wife had a massive\ncollection of shoes, which was left behind after the People’s Power Revolution. For 10 points,\nname this Asian nation which was formerly ruled by Ferdinand Marcos.",
        "answer": "the Philippines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Philippines was devastated by Yolanda in 2013, a kind of which storm?",
        "answer": "Typhoon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This procedure occurred to the writer of Forever Amber and Laura. This process required the\nauthor of Johnny Get You Gun to adopt the alias \"Robert Rich.\" For 10 points, name this process\nwhich was performed on Ring Lardner, Jr., Dalton Trumbo, and others in the Hollywood Ten,\nwho were denied work in the film industry due to their membership in the Communist Party.",
        "answer": [
          "blacklisting",
          "blacklist"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Trumbo was publicly acknowledged as the writer of what 1961 slave uprising drama\nstarring Kirk Douglas, ending the blacklist?",
        "answer": "Spartacus"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE MAURYAN EMPIRE",
      "prompt": "The Mauryan empire...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "was on what subcontinent later home to the British Raj?",
          "answer": [
            "Indian subcontinent",
            "India"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "put edicts on rocks and what structures which can be Doric or Corinthian?",
          "answer": [
            "pillars",
            "columns"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "heard of Ashoka's conversion to what religion founded by Siddartha Gautama?",
          "answer": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Buddhist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was founded by what king who fought Seleucus Nicator?",
          "answer": [
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Chandragupta"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "used what refined language in which the Arthashastra was written?",
          "answer": [
            "Sanskrit language",
            "Sanskrit",
            "Samskrtam",
            "Samskrta"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "sent emissaries to what island later home to the Jaffna, Kotte, and Kandy kingdoms?",
          "answer": [
            "Sri Lanka",
            "Ceylon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "fought what type of local governors used by Persia and the Seleucids to its west?",
          "answer": [
            "satraps",
            "satrapies"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "used what capital city, as did the Nanda and Gupta empires?",
          "answer": "Pataliputra"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE CONGRESS OF VIENNA",
      "prompt": "During or after the Congress of Vienna, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French emperor was exiled to Saint Helena?",
          "answer": [
            "Napoleon Bonaparte",
            "Napoleon",
            "Napoleon I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian statesmen hosted the forum?",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who was victorious at Waterloo joined Castlereagh in representing the UK?",
          "answer": [
            "Arthur Wellesley",
            "Wellesley",
            "the Duke of Wellington",
            "Wellington"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Czar of Russia led the Russian delegation?",
          "answer": "Alexander I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country retained control of the Cape Colony and Tobago?",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Minister for Louis XVIII headed the French delegation?",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Maurice de Talleyrand",
            "Talleyrand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country regained control of Tyrol and Ragusa?",
          "answer": "Austria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country was represented by Cael Lowenhielm, an illegitimate son of its king Charles XIII?",
          "answer": "Sweden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BREAKAWAY REGIONS",
      "prompt": "Who or what is or was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Oil-rich African country with capital at Abuja which Biafra broke away from?",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central Asian nation which has breakaway regions in Abkhazia and South Ossetia and shares\nits name with a U.S. sate?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Catalan separatists have been protesting in Barcelona?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Middle East ethnic group who have tried to break off from Turkey and have autonomy within\nIraq?",
          "answer": [
            "Kurds",
            "Kurdish"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country targeted by the Western Sahara independence movement?",
          "answer": "Morocco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian country which seized Goa from the Portuguese?",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "French-speaking West African country where Azawad tried to secede in 2012?",
          "answer": "Mali"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disputed region fought over by Armenia and Azerbaijan in a 1991 war?",
          "answer": "Nagorno-Karabakh"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In mid-2014, popular examples of this kind of product included the Moto 360 and Pebble\nSteel. Samsung launched several of these products under the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Gear\" line, and these\nproducts are named for a Sony line that integrates with (10 pts) ",
        "Android operating systems. For\n10 points, Apple caused a stir by announcing the launch of their version of what kind of wearable\ntechnology product, which is often used for fitness monitoring or portable media capabilities?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "smart watches"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s father was an Olympic boxer for Iran, while he himself won the 1996\nOlympic gold medal in men’s singles for tennis. In the early 1990’s, he attracted\ncontroversy for his flamboyant (20 pts) ",
        "dress, but also gained an endorsement deal for Canon\ncameras where he said the tagline, “Image is everything.” He is the most recent American\nto achieve the career (10 pts) ",
        "Grand Slam, and he is married to German legend Steffi Graf. For 10\npoints, name this tennis player and Las Vegas native, who was perhaps the greatest rival to Pete\nSampras."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Andre Agassi",
        "Agassi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Norse mythology, it was believed that the world-ending Ragnarok would include the\nwolf Skoll finally succeeding in his quest to eat this object. The national god of the Incas,\nInti, was the god of this thing. Japanese (20 pts) ",
        "emperors once titled themselves as descendants\nof a goddess of this thing, (10 pts) ",
        "Amaterasu. Similarly, Egyptians placed great importance on the\nmain god of this thing, Ra. For 10 points, name this astronomical body often worshipped by\npolytheists."
      ],
      "answer": "the sun"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was embarrassed by the 2002 release of Nixon White House tapes in which he\naccused Jews of belonging to the \"synagogue of Satan.\" This man, who has taken credit for\nconvincing Dwight Eisenhower to (20 pts) ",
        "desegregate schools in Arkansas, became famous for\nhis Festival of Hope and (10 pts) ",
        "ecumenical revivals, which close with the hymn \"Just As I Am.\"\nFor 10 points, name this frequent Presidential advisor and most successful evangelist in\nAmerican history."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Billy Graham",
        "Graham"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this film, the title character builds a Chicago opera house in an attempt to make his\nsecond wife, Susan Alexander, into a movie star. Jerry Thompson attempts to research the\nlife of this film’s title character, who had built the (20 pts) ",
        "Xanadu estate. This movie begins\nwith its title character dropping a snowglobe after whispering the word (10 pts) ",
        "“Rosebud.” For\n10 points, name this Orson Welles movie about a newspaper magnate."
      ],
      "answer": "Citizen Kane"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man replaced Vin Diesel in the lead role for the sequel XxX: State of the Union. This\nman was attacked by his former bandmates on the EP 100 Miles and Runnin at the same\ntime that he released his solo debut, (20 pts) ",
        "AmeriKKKa's Most Wanted. This star of the (10 pts) ",
        "Barbershop series wrote more lyrics for NWA than any other member. For 10 points, name this\ngangsta rapper turned family comedian, the star of the Are We There Yet? movies."
      ],
      "answer": "Ice Cube"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man commissioned a battle flag with a motto sewn on it that he attributed to James\nLawrence, \"Don't Give Up the Ship.\" This man opposed Jesse Elliot, the captain of the\nNiagara, at (20 pts) ",
        "Put-In Bay. He issued the message \"We have (10 pts) ",
        "met the enemy and they are\nours\" to his commander in the field, William Henry Harrison. For 10 points, name this naval\ncommander who defeated the British at the Battle of Lake Erie during the War of 1812."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Oliver Hazard Perry",
        "Perry"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's central bank adopted a policy of “forward guidance” for future interest\nrates after the 2008 financial crisis. It froze Icelandic bank assets in 2008 after Iceland\nrefused to guarantee its banks' debts to creditors in this country. The Chancellor of the (20 pts) ",
        "Exchequer proposed large spending cuts in 2010 as part of the austerity program of its\nformer prime minister, (10 pts) ",
        "David Cameron. For 10 points, name this country whose\ngovernment nationalized the Royal Bank of Scotland."
      ],
      "answer": "United Kingdom"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Charles Ogle mockingly accused Martin van Buren of eating with a spoon made of these\nsubstance. A speech about this substance exclaimed \"you shall not press down upon the\nbrow of labor this (20 pts) ",
        "crown of thorns.\" This substance was sought by men who went to the (10 pts) ",
        "Klondike, the 49ers, and other prospectors. For 10 points, name this substance whose\n\"standard\" was, until 1971, the basis of American money."
      ],
      "answer": "gold"
    }
  ]
}